Better understand how self-awareness can
shift from a source of overthinking and
suffering to a source of meaning and
wonder through my new book, The Terrible
Paradox of Self-Awareness. The link is
in the description.
One must imagine Sisyphus [music] happy.
This is the final line of writer and
philosopher Albert Camus' famous work,
The Myth of Sisyphus.
You've likely seen or heard it before,
even if you're not familiar with his
work, as this line has transcended its
origins
>> [music]
>> and can now be found in comment sections
and memes all across the internet,
pasted into different contexts, images,
and conversations.
But what exactly does this line mean?
What exactly was Camus trying to say?
Sisyphus is a Greek king condemned by
the gods to roll a boulder up a hill,
only for it to roll back down as soon as
he approaches the top, over and over for
eternity. [music]
Why would we imagine such a person
happy? For what reasons would he be?
Is Camus wrong? Is Sisyphus dumb?
At its core, the line is a sort of hymn
for the school of thought [music] known
as absurdism, a philosophy that Camus is
largely credited with defining.
The philosophy can essentially be summed
up with the following.
Humanity has an innate desire for
meaning and truth,
>> [music]
>> a rational understanding of everything.
Yet the universe appears entirely devoid
of these things.
>> [music]
>> The absurd is found in the conflict
between humanity's desire and what is,
our yearning for rationality meeting the
universe's irrationality, our pleading
for meaning
>> [music]
>> and the universe's cold silence.
Camus writes,
"In a universe suddenly divested of
illusions and lights,
>> [music]
>> man feels an alien, a stranger. His
exile is without remedy, since he is
deprived of the memory of a lost home or
the hope of a promised land."
>> [music]
>> Camus chooses Sisyphus as the
quintessential allegorical embodiment of
this absurd condition. He uses the myth
to explore and arrive at what he argues
is the resolution to humanity's
confrontation with the absurd.
To better understand where, [music] how,
and what Camus arrives at, and whether
it suffices, Let's start with a brief
summary of Sisyphus' [music] story.
In Greek mythology, Sisyphus was the
founder and king of Ephyra, now known as
Corinth.
He was an extremely clever, but
tyrannical king, often killing visitors
and inappropriately seducing women.
His hubris was so immense, he also often
meddled with the gods.
In one case, he undermined the sky and
thunder god, Zeus, by conspiring with
the river god, Asopus.
This didn't go over very well.
Sisyphus' behavior would eventually lead
Zeus to having him taken to the
underworld.
Sisyphus, however, being as clever as he
was, fooled the god of death, Thanatos,
by convincing him to demonstrate how the
chains for his punishment worked. In the
process, Sisyphus bound the chains
around Thanatos and escaped the
underworld.
After much commotion and chaos as a
result of Sisyphus' actions, trapping
the god of death, he knew that his
escape would eventually come to a head
once Thanatos was freed.
And so, Sisyphus conceived of another
plan to avoid facing any consequences.
He ordered his wife, Merope, to toss his
body into the public square once he died
of natural causes.
His wife did as instructed.
Once back in the underworld, Sisyphus
informed the queen, Persephone, that he
had been disrespected by not receiving a
proper burial.
His plan worked, and Persephone allowed
Sisyphus to return to the land of the
living to punish his wife, so long as he
immediately returned after.
Sisyphus did not return.
He believed he had triumphed over death
and outsmarted the gods yet again. But
Sisyphus would soon realize the gods can
be tricked, but not beaten. Zeus would
catch Sisyphus and punish him once and
for all, where now he could no longer
escape or outsmart anything.
Enforced by divine authority, his
punishment, the absurd condition the
modern world has come to know him for,
rolling a massive boulder up a hill,
where every time he approaches the top,
it rolls back down to the bottom, and he
must start again.
Over and over,
forever.
Sisyphus is a striking choice for Camus
to embody the condition humanity finds
itself in, particularly in the modern
world. So much of life is comprised of
tiny boulders reminiscent [music] of
Sisyphus's plight. From cleaning the
house and paying the bills to day-to-day
routines and work to career benchmarks,
social achievements, and relationships
to humanity's technological and
scientific progress.
These all have a kind of looping
futility to them. They fail and [music]
or lead to new problems. Even if we
accomplish them, we find ourselves
essentially back where we started,
bored, confused, and desiring of
something we can't [music] quite satiate
or put our finger on.
And of course, all will ultimately be
crushed under the weight of the one
giant boulder that is life itself.
Everything we do and accomplish,
everyone we love, everything we learn,
obtain, or think we've made sense of
>> [music]
>> will turn to dust underneath the boulder
of our mortal transience. And if we see
no obvious afterlife, no obvious order
in the universe, no ultimate answers to
our why questions, it all seems to go
nowhere.
Back down the hill.
Camus writes, "To work and create for
nothing,
>> [music]
>> to sculpture in clay, to know that one's
creation has no future, to see one's
work destroyed in a day while being
aware that fundamentally [music]
this is no more importance than building
for centuries.
This is the difficult wisdom that absurd
[music] thought sanctions."
So back to the question,
if this is Sisyphus's story, an eternal
condition, and this is what Camus is
paralleling to humanity's condition, why
must one imagine him happy? What about
this condition gives any reason to
believe in the possibility
>> [music]
>> of happiness?
There are of course many interpretations
one can make about Sisyphus's
psychological state and Camus's
philosophical intention. It's helpful to
first ground those interpretations in
the cultural and historical context in
which Camus was writing in.
Born in French Algeria in 1913, he grew
up during a period of of cultural
volatility and change. Between the world
wars and the increasing collapse of
societal structures, Camus existed in a
world comprising heavy hearts and
unstable ground.
In adulthood, he had become a major
figure a part of the existentialist
movement, helping form its shape and
popularity alongside the likes of
philosophers like Jean-Paul Sartre,
Simone de Beauvoir, and Martin
Heidegger.
Fundamentally, the existentialist view
is that life has no inherent meaning,
and meaning can only be forged
subjectively through human choice and
action rather than discovered as an
external truth.
In the words of Jean-Paul Sartre, in
life, a man commits himself, draws his
own portrait, and there is nothing but
that portrait.
During this time, humanity began to find
itself increasingly consumed by a shadow
cast by the carcasses of progress and
religion. Nihilism was taking the form
of the shadow, and existentialism and
subsequently [music] absurdism were
trying to find the edges of light.
After all, it's one thing to endure the
pains and hardships of existence when
you believe there is a grand purpose to
everything. When a heaven awaits. When
meaning is there for you in your first
breath and carrying you softly into your
last. But when the fabric tears,
dropping you into the abyss of
uncertainty and unintelligibility, what
are you left to do but fall into
despair?
The things you can't understand or do,
the struggles and terrors of existence,
all retain their pain but lose their
meaning.
Camus' attempt to deal with this fall,
to weave a kind of non-lethal safety
net, was through absurdism.
He writes,
"The realization that life is absurd
cannot be an end, but only a beginning.
This is a truth nearly all great minds
have taken as their starting point. It
is not this discovery that is
interesting, but the consequences and
rules of action drawn from it."
Camus' broader argument with Sisyphus is
that rather than despairing over his
condition, if Sisyphus acknowledges it
with lucidity, recognizing and embracing
its total absurdity,
>> [music]
>> and refuses to depend on grand illusions
about some better tomorrow in which the
boulder will hold or new life will come,
and continues on anyway. He triumphs
over his condition. He revolts against
it with his happiness. That is, his
happiness is part and parcel of his
triumph and revolt, rather than an
outcome of it.
Likewise, for Camus, we should revolt
against our futile condition, against
nihilism, with the kind of defiant joy.
An endeavor to spiritedly continue, not
in denial of the absurdity of our lives,
but in the face of it, embracing it
without languishing.
This is perhaps where one might find
themselves unsatisfied with such a
conclusion. On the surface, without
further context, analysis, or
interpretation, this can almost feel
like a form of just be happy advice.
What if one can't imagine Sisyphus
happy? What if one can't imagine
themselves happy? Where does one go from
there? Is it hopeless? As I write in my
book, The Terrible Paradox of
Self-Awareness, [music]
we want more than the individual meaning
and purpose we imagine for ourselves. We
want more than to imagine we are happy.
We want the boulder to go somewhere
else, to mean something else.
Part of the problem, it seems, is
Camus's choice of words here.
Happy simply does not appear to be the
appropriate term. And within the work,
Camus does not clearly define it to mean
anything beyond the definition we tend
to associate it with. That is, the
feeling of pleasure.
Even a broader definition of happiness,
like content, still seems to be a bit
off, at least on its own.
Sisyphus is both in and aware of a
wretched condition, and he's not a fool.
He's smart to a fault. And continuing to
strive something over and over, by force
or otherwise, seems somewhat
antithetical to contentment, at least
without imagining other things about
him.
And perhaps that's what we should do.
Rather than mere happiness, Sisyphus's
ideal and realistic state [music] can be
understood best through total
acceptance.
Camus writes,
"The absurd [music] man thus catches
sight of a burning and frigid,
transparent and limited universe, in
which nothing is possible, but
everything is given, and beyond which
all is collapse and nothingness. [music]
He can then decide to accept such a
universe and draw from it his strength,
>> [music]
>> his refusal to hope, and the unyielding
evidence of a life without consolation.
Sisyphus has [music] no choice in his
condition, and so his choices become
limited to the framework of his
perspective and attention. [music]
Though it is arguably a big leap to
suggest that from here he can brute
force his way to happiness through
merely withstanding or revolting [music]
against his condition, there's something
profound still to be maintained here.
In radical acceptance,
>> [music]
>> Sisyphus can begin relieving the tension
between himself and his conditions,
freeing up his mental space and energy
[music]
to determine a better way to engage with
his conditions.
This approach is supported in modern
psychotherapy with an evidence-based
model, ACT, acceptance and commitment
therapy.
The model works by first encouraging
individuals to open up to and accept
their negative feelings and thoughts,
rather than resisting them.
In doing so, it is found that one can
form a better relationship with their
thoughts and feelings, creating a kind
of distance between them and one's
awareness or sense [music] of self.
Thoughts and feelings become like
passing objects in a sea of mental and
bodily activity, of which the individual
observes, rather than controls or
attaches [music] to.
This approach to self-awareness is what
is known in the model as self as
context, [music]
which differs from the more typical
conception of oneself as being one in
the same as their thoughts and feelings,
[music]
which is known as self as content. For
Sisyphus, self as content might entail
an attitude like the following.
I am rolling this rock up this hill for
no reason. What I am doing [music] is
pointless. I'm pointless. Everything is
pointless.
Whereas self as context might entail
something like,
>> [music]
>> I'm experiencing thoughts about why I'm
rolling this rock up this hill for no
reason. But my thoughts are not me, and
this condition is something I am
observing. [music]
This may seem like a semantic slight of
hand, and that's fair. But in the
latter, there's a gap created between
phenomena and perception, awareness.
[music]
And within this gap, we can change the
quality of our responses to our
experiences. [music]
In some cases, when we can, this might
mean stopping rolling the rock up the
hill. In other cases, it might mean
orienting our perception differently
about the process of rolling the rock.
ACT suggests that we calibrate our
awareness according to our values, be it
curiosity, creativity, wonder, or
compassion.
In other words, once we've accepted our
condition, or at least what we cannot
change, we still can and must decide
what we should do and what we should
care about within our [music]
constraints. In this, we paradoxically
reclaim ownership over our situations.
We go from using our energy to resist or
deny reality, or attempting to withstand
it heroically, to flowing with it and
orienting ourselves in simultaneously
real and productive terms.
Perhaps Sisyphus might try to be the
best rock roller he can, paying close
attention to each step and each push,
getting better and better each time.
Perhaps he might try to consider as many
perspectives and interpretations as he
can during each roll, every angle of all
the aspects and details of the landscape
around him. Perhaps he might try to
engage in the wonder and nature of the
situation with no dependency on ever
comprehending it fully.
Perhaps he might pride himself on not
harming any bug or creature on [music]
the hill.
Perhaps he might make ornate shaping,
art, out of the paths formed by the rock
rolling.
Perhaps he might try to forget the rock
and focus on each step, each breath,
each moment, moving with the utmost
presence. Each push, a kind of mantra
for the silence of all [music] things.
Crucially, though this parallels Camus'
philosophical framework, it arguably
isn't happiness we are left with,
[music] nor in pursuit of. Rather, it is
sort of a non-attachment to happiness
and unhappiness. It is a movement toward
the frequent dissolvment of the very
question of happiness and unhappiness.
"Am I happy?" is one of those questions
that, if it has got to be asked,
>> [music]
>> more or less dictates its own answer.
Wrote author David Foster Wallace.
To be fair, Camus is arguably producing
a work of literature here as much as he
is philosophy. In fact, Camus rejected
the title of philosopher stating,
"I am not a philosopher because I don't
believe in reason enough to believe in a
system."
Any ambiguity or contradiction in his
work is likely, in some sense,
intentional or at least accepted for the
very purpose of further interpretation.
This openness and provocation of thought
leaves room to
and affirm his ideas simultaneously.
Like with Camus' conclusion, this still
isn't a resolution of nihilism or
meaninglessness.
We are still left without consolation in
the form of objective meaning or truth.
But it is arguably a more stable kind of
resolution. A paradoxical relief from
the dependency on any ultimate meaning,
truth, and happiness. [music]
In the end, like Sisyphus, we have no
choice. We have no choice in being born,
the nature of our minds and bodies, and
the conditions of the world and
universe. We too must accept what is
happening, what we find ourselves in.
>> [music]
>> We too must be aware of the phenomena
comprising an existence inside a human,
inside a world.
>> [music]
>> It is our blessing and our curse
to see, conceptualize, and hope, but to
never control, resolve, [music] or know.
But we can still choose values within
the space of our awareness without
having to ground them in objective
meaning.
And we can still use them to orient
ourselves toward the heights not of a
hill,
but of being.
Perhaps, in the end, the line could
read,
"One must imagine [music] Sisyphus
present. One must imagine him focused.
One must imagine him enthralled with
wonder.
>> [music]
>> One must imagine Sisyphus, even if only
for brief moments,
not imagining anything at all,
but simply being."
One of the most important things we can
do in life is learn how to better
understand and live with our awareness,
the way we experience ourselves in the
world. This can often be painful and
convoluted. But if faced head-on, it can
also lead to greater depths and
qualities of experience, helping us turn
our self-awareness from a source of
constant overthinking, anxiety, regret,
and suffering to a source of wonder and
poise. My new book, The Terrible Paradox
of Self-Awareness,
attempts to do just that. It's a kind of
philosophical thought map that pulls
from my years of research on various
schools of thought, from Taoism to
Buddhism to existentialism to absurdism
and more, all synthesized into one
unique exploration of awareness [music]
and existence. It doesn't sugarcoat
things, and it doesn't provide easy
answers, but it attempts to engage with
existence through a kind of compassion,
openness, and radical embrace, so we can
still find our way toward experiencing a
life that's worth it. If you're
interested, the link is in the
description below.
And of course, as always, thank you so
much for watching in general, and see
you next video.